HANS SIMONS PAPERS (GER082) 1906-1968
M. E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives
Hans Simons Papers1906-1968
nam_ger082
German-born Political Science professor who emigrated to America in 1935, became professor and president for the New School.
Simons, Hans, 1893-1972
0.5
M. E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, University at Albany, SUNY
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, by Gerhard Simons in 1981. 1981
Biographical History
Hans Simons was a German-born political scholar who came to America in 1935 after he was blacklisted by the Nazis. He joined The New School's University in Exile's faculty, and became an American citizen in 1940. Simons was appointed president of The New School in 1945.
Scope and Content Information
Includes diary, 1935-1937; typescripts of articles and lectures on education and politics, 1919-1963; and offprints.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection has no series, arranged chronologically.
Subject and Genre Headings
Political Science; Political Science; Political Science; Political Science; Political Science; Political Science; Political Science; Political Science; Political Science; Political Science; Political Science; Political Science; Political Science; Political Science; Political Science; Political Science; Political Science; Political Science; Political Science; Political Science; Political Science; Political Science; Political Science; Political Science; Political Science; Political Science; Political Science; Political Science; Simons, Hans, 1893-1972; Stresemann, Gustav, 1878-1929; New School for Social Research (New York, N.Y.); University in Exile.; Treaty of Versailles (1919); World War, 1939-1945 -- Refugees.; Political science -- Study and teaching.; Europe -- Politics and government -- 1918-1945.
Container List
- Education, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Doctoral dissertation: Die Praembel zur Pariser Vlkerbundssatzung und das Vkerrecht, Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Employment, Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Diary covering his crossing of the Atlantic, trip from the East to West Coast, and trip to Canada, 1935 January-1937 October (Box 1, Folder 4)
- The New School for Social Research, 1952-1958; Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
- "Universitt im Exil", Undated
- "Text of Address by Dr. Hans Simons, President, New School for Social Research at annual. commencement exercises (Photocopy of typescript), 1952 June 3
- "Future of The New School." (Carbon of typescript), 1958 September 18
- "On the Functions and the Future of The New School As It Completes Its Building Program and Prepares Itself For New Educational Tasks." Report of the President to the Board of Trustees (Photocopy of typescript), 1958 September 26
- Manuscripts and lectures, 1919-1951; Undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
- "In einer Woche soll sich zeigen..." (Carbon), 1919 May 30
- "Verfassungsrede 1932" (Carbon of typescript)
- "Lecture by Professor Hans Simons In support of the United Nations" (Typescript), 1947 January 7
- "Does America Understand its International Public Relations Responsibilities?" (Photocopy of typescript), 1951 April 25
- "Since my first report..." (Carbon of typescript), 1951 August 1
- "Political Science in German Universities: A Report" (Photocopy of typescript), Undated
- "Regierung, Parteien und Wehrmacht 1918 bis 1932" (Typescript), Undated
- "Reichsreform Was steckt dahinter?" (Typescript), Undated
- "When Germans want to acknowledge" (Typescript), Undated
- Indian education, 1960-1964 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- "Biographical Information on Dr. Hans Simons" (Prepared for his participation in India with the University Grants Commission), ca. 1960-1962
- "The Present Indian Response to the Problem of General Education" (Typescript), 1960 December
- "Comments to the Draft Report of the Expert Committee on General Education" (Carbon of typescript), 1960 December
- "Abstract from Remarks Made at the Conference on Higher Education in Bombay" (Typescript), 1960 December
- "Suggestions about the Reform of General Education at Aligarh" (Typescript), 1961 May 8
- "Considerations concerning the present situation of general education in Indian Universities" (Carbon of typescript), 1961 September 29
- "Suggested items to be discussed and Policies to be Decided upon at a Meeting of Those Concerned with, the Reading Material Project at Aligarh Muslim University" Draft (Carbon of typescript), 1961 November 15
- "Essentials of a General Education Program" A statement requested by the Vice-Chancellor of Rajasthan University (Typescript), 1961 November 2
- "Comments to draft-outline of syllabus sent in by Rajasthan University" Dr. V. P. S. Raghuvamshi (Carbon of typescript), 1962 January 11
- "Report on General Education 1960/62" (Carbon of typescript), 1962 October 3
- "Study for What?" (Typescript), 1962 March 10
- "General Education Seminar Held at Panjab University on October 5th & 6th" (Carbon of typescript), 1962 October 6
- "Resolutions Adopted at Panjab University Seminar on General Education" (Carbon of typescript), ca. 1962 October 6
- "Copy of a letter from Dr. Hans Simons addressed to Dr. D. circa Pavate, Vice-Chancellor, Karnatak University" (Typescript), 1963 February 27
- "Concerning Standards of University Education" (Typescript), 1963 October 10
- "Concerning Standards of University Education" (Photocopy of typescript), 1963 October
- "The Meaning of General Education: Call It What You Will But Do Something About It" (Carbon of typescript), ca. 1963
- "Task Force for Higher Education Comments on the Working Paper" (Carbon of typescript), 1964 December 2
- "General Education in Indian Universities" (Typescript), Undated
- "I. Universities where rather intensive work was done through visits and often voluminous correspondence" (Typescript), Undated
- Offprints, Undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Manuscript by F. S. Friedmann. "Introduction to UNLA: An Experiment in Community Improvement through Adult Education" (Photocopy of typescript), 1959 February 16 (Box 1, Folder 9)